議案根據《適宜及通則條例》就修訂仲裁委任仲裁員及調解員和決定仲裁員人數規定而動議嘅二二決議案，有意就議案發言嘅議員請按下要求發言按鈕。我現在請律政司。
司長發言及動議議案，律政司司長。
主席，我動議通過上述嘅議案。該議案嘅內容已經喺發放畀各位議員嘅文件裏邊列出。呢項議案建議修訂仲裁（括弧委任仲裁員及調解員和決定仲裁員人數括弧規則）。
響取得中審法院首席法官嘅事先批准之後，香港國際仲裁中心根據二零一一年六月一日起生效嘅《仲裁條例》第六百零九章第十三條第三款訂立呢一套嘅規則。
該規則係依據現行嘅仲裁（括弧仲裁員及公斷人的委任）（括弧）規則第三百四十一章附屬法例大綱B作出修改而到去制定嘅。呢一套嘅規則旨在便利香港國際仲裁中心履行以下嘅。
嘅職能，第一係根據新嘅仲裁條例第二十四條，響規定需委任嘅仲裁員未有被委出嘅時候，由香港國際仲裁中心委任仲裁員。第二根據新嘅仲裁條例第二十三條第三款，由
由香港國際仲裁中心決定仲裁員嘅人數，以及係三根據仲裁條例第三十二條第一款，響規定需委任嘅調解員未有被委出嘅時候，由香港國際仲裁中心委任調查員。
規則響二零一三年七月三日提交立法會審覽，立法會內務委員會隨後成立小組委員會審議呢項嘅規則。響二零一三年九月十八號嘅立法會小組委員會會議裏邊，香港國際香港國際仲裁中心嘅代表。
同意小組委員會法律顧問嘅建議，對呢一套嘅規則作出若干嘅修訂，而呢啲修訂亦都得到小組委員會嘅支持。
大部分嘅建議修訂都係對有關嘅規則嘅內容嘅中英文嘅文本作出草草擬方面嘅修訂，唔會影響有關條文嘅實質內容。政府當局對呢啲建議修訂並無異議。喺呢個情況之下，我提出呢一項議案就香港。
講國際仲裁中心同埋小組委員會所同意嘅建議，對規出對規則作出修訂。我僅藉呢一個機會，向小組委員會主席郭榮亨議員同埋其他嘅成員致意，感謝佢哋喺呢方面所付出嘅努力。主席，我僅此動議通過。
案，多謝。
我現在向各位提出嘅代議議題係律政司司長動議嘅議案，予以通過。郭榮亨議員。
啊，郭榮亨議員。
Thank you, acting. Thank you, acting president. In my capacity as chairman of the subcommittee on arbitration (appointment of arbitrators and mediators and decision on number of arbitrators), rules, I report on the main deliberations of the subcommittee. The arbitration rules are made under section 13, subsection.
三， of the arbitration ordinance to repeal the arbitration.
appointment of arbitrators and umpire roosts and substitute them with a new set of roosts to make provisions to facilitate the Hong Kong International Arbitration Centre to perform its statutory functions, namely making the appointment of arbitrators and decision on the number of arbitrators for parties to an arbitration.
The subcommittee has held one meeting to discuss with the administration and received views from the relevant stakeholders. Members generally support the rules. Members note that stakeholders, including the two legal professional bodies, generally support the rules, and organisations such as the Hong Kong IAC have urged for its early implementation.
係。
The subcommittee notes that in the course of an arbitration, parties to an arbitration may apply for the appointment of a mediator by the HKIAC to expediate the settlement of the dispute.
The subcommittee is concerned about the protection of the interests of parties to arbitration when a mediator so appointed is subsequently appointed as an arbitrator for the same case. The Hong Kong IAC has advised that whenever mediation is adopted, the parties undertake that the mediation must proceed in accordance with the mediation rules and that.
The failure by any mediators to abide by the mediation rules will lead to serious consequences, such as disqualification of the mediator concerned. Some members questioned the need for Rule 13, Subrule 2 of the rules, which empowers the Hong Kong IAC to increase its fee from time to time up to a ceiling of US$15,000.
Without requiring the new fee to be subject to scrutiny by the council or published in the gazette, the subcommittee notes that the Hong Kong IAC has not been able to locate any example from existing legislative provisions which similarly allow fees or charges specified in primary or subsidiary legislation to be varied administratively.
Without requiring the new amounts to be subject to positive or negative vetting by the council or published in the gazette, the Hong Kong IAC advised that the policy intent of Rule 13 Subrule 2 is not to tailor a fee each time the Hong Kong IAC exercises statutory functions, but rather to review the cost periodic
to ensure that the Hong Kong IAC is not making a significant loss in the overall performance of its statutory functions. The Hong Kong IAC does not foresee the need to raise the $15,000 ceiling of the fees in the near future. If there is a need to further raise the $15,000 ceiling, the Hong Kong IAC will publish a new set of
提出修正案，供本會審議。在審議過程中，成員表達了對香港現在輸給我們主要競爭對手新加坡作為亞洲頂級國際調解中心的擔憂。
The subcommittee is of the view that the Hong Kong arbitration sector deserves more support, and that the Hong Kong government has not put in adequate resources, not nearly enough, an effort into.
promoting our arbitration capabilities and institutions. And to be fair to the secretary for justice, I know they have been working hard, but simply simply requires more of a political will on the part of government to do more to promote and to push Hong Kong as the premium Asian international dispute resolution.
諮詢中心，to tie in with the government's policy to promote Hong Kong as a legal and arbitration service centre in the Asia-Pacific region, we urge the administration to provide more support to the arbitration sector and to institutions such as the Hong Kong IAC.
The administration will move amendments to Rule 13, Subrule 2 of the rules to better reflect the policy intent of that rule, and to certain provisions of the rules to improve their drafting. Members of the subcommittee agree to the administration's amendments. Acting President, the above is my report on the subcommittee's work, and I shall now express my personal view.
on rules. In fact, I have already done so earlier in reiterating the importance of supporting and promoting Hong Kong's international arbitration services and capabilities, which will not only benefit the Hong Kong legal profession but also the Hong Kong public. President, I.
Those are my speech. Thank you.
有冇其他議員想發言？
如果冇啊，現在請律政司司長發言答辯。喺律政司司長答發答辯之後，辯論即告結束。律政司司長。
主席，誒多謝郭榮亨議員頭先所講有關香港作為國際仲裁中心嘅事題。
誒，我哋律政司一直係非常關注呢一方面嘅問題，亦都我同我嘅同事係盡我哋最大嘅努力，係為香港鞏固作為亞太區國際仲裁中心呢一方面嘅工作，希望呢一方面嘅工作日後可以同大家立法會嘅議員，包括郭榮亨議。
員同埋兩個律師團隊，同埋香港有關仲裁嘅機構，大家再共同攜手協力，係做好呢個工作。多謝主席。
我現在向各位提出嘅代決議題係律政司司長動議嘅議案，予以通過。現在付諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲。